<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document>

    &project;

    <properties>
      <author>Remy Maucherat</author>
      <title>Building Tomcat</title>
    </properties>

<body>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>
Building Tomcat from CVS is very easy, and is the first step to contributing to
Tomcat. The following is a step by step TODO list.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Download and install a Java Development Kit 1.4.x or later">

<p>
Earlier releases would also work, but are harder to work with due to the need to
download additional dependencies. Tomcat also runs much faster on 
the latest 1.4 JDK.
</p>

<p>
The Sun JDK can be downloaded <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
<b>IMPORTANT</b>: Set an environment variable JAVA_HOME to the pathname of the 
directory into which you installed the JDK release.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Install Apache Ant 1.6.x">

<p>
Download a binary distribution of Ant 1.6.x from 
<a href="http://ant.apache.org/bindownload.cgi">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
Unpack the binary distribution into a convenient location so that the
Ant release resides in its own directory (conventionally named
"jakarta-ant-1.6.2").  For the purposes of the remainder of this document,
the symbolic name "${ant.home}" is used to refer to the full pathname of
 the release directory.
</p>

<p>
Create an ANT_HOME environment variable to point the directory ${ant.home}, 
and modify the PATH environment variable to include directory
"${ant.home}/bin" in its list.  This makes the "ant" command line script
available, which will be used to actually perform the build.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Building Tomcat">

<p>
Download the main build.xml script from <a href="build.xml">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
Create a new directory, and copy the newly download build.xml to it. This
  directory will be referred to as the ${tomcat.source} directory in the rest
  of this document.
</p>

<p>
Go to that directory, and do:
<code><br/>
    cd ${tomcat.source}<br/>
    ant<br/>
</code>
</p>

<p>
NOTE: Users accessing the Internet through a proxy must use a properties
  file to indicate to Ant the proxy configuration. Read below.
</p>

<p>
WARNING: Running this command will checkout the Tomcat 5 sources from CVS, as
  well as download binaries to the <code>/usr/share/java</code> directory. 
  Make sure this is appropriate to do so on your computer. On Windows, 
  this usually corresponds to the <code>C:\usr\share\java</code> directory, 
  unless Cygwin is used. Read below to customize the directory used 
  to download the binaries.
</p>

<p>
The build can be controlled by creating a ${tomcat.source}/build.properties
  file, and adding the following content to it:
<code><br/>
    # ----- Proxy setup -----<br/>
    # Uncomment if using a proxy server.<br/>
    #proxy.host=proxy.domain<br/>
    #proxy.port=8080<br/>
    #proxy.use=on<br/>
<br/>
    # ----- Default Base Path for Dependent Packages -----<br/>
    # Replace this path with the directory path where<br/>
    # dependencies binaries should be downloaded.<br/>
    base.path=/usr/share/java<br/>
</code>
</p>

</section>

<section name="Updating and rebuilding Tomcat sources">

<p>
It is recommended to regularly update the downloaded Tomcat 5 sources. 
To do this, execute the following commands:

<code><br/>
    cd ${tomcat.source}<br/>
    ant checkout<br/>
</code>
</p>

<p>
For a quick rebuild of only modified code you can use:
<code><br/>
    cd ${tomcat.source}<br/>
    ant build<br/>
</code>

</p>

</section>

<section name="Building with Eclipse">

<p>
<b>Important:</b>
This is not a supported means of building Tomcat; this information is
provided without warranty :-).
The only supported means of building Tomcat is with the "ant build"
described above.
However, some developers like to work on Java code with a Java IDE,
and the following steps have been used by some developers.
</p>

<p>
Note that you <b>must</b> complete all the above steps to fetch
the repositories and build some JAR files the first time.
After you have completed the above steps, you can set up a
series of Eclipse 3 projects.
<b>Note</b> that this will not let you build everything under Eclipse;
the build process requires use of Ant for the many stages that aren't
simple Java compilations.
However, it will allow you to view and edit the Java code,
get warnings, reformat code, perform refactorings, run Tomcat
under the IDE, and so on.
</p>

<p>
Use File-&gt;New Project to create a new Java project 
for each of the binaries repository (e.g., /usr/share/java), 
tomcat-connectors, tomcat-catalina, jasper, servletapi.
Unless you thought ahead to make the ${tomcat.source} directory be under
your Workspace folder, tell Eclipse the external location.
The obvious dependencies will be needed; the "repository" project
needs to export all its jars, and be referred to by the other projects.
Eclipse will find all source trees and jars, and
hopefully compile without problems
You will need to add ${ant-home}/lib/ant.jar as an "External Jar"
under Project Properties for some of these projects (notably those that fail
to compile for want of BuildException).
</p>

<p>
To run Tomcat without a special IDE plug-in, you can simply use Run-&gt;Run...
enter "org.apache.catalina.startup.Catalina" as the main class,
"start" as program arguments, and
"-Dcatalina.home=..." (with the name of your build directory) 
as VM arguments.
</p>

<p>
Note also that due to the way the Tomcat source is assembled
from several CVS projects, you may not be able to use the Eclipse
CVS client to update (nor to commit, if you are a committer).
Use the external CVS client of your choice, then use the
Eclipse PackageExplorer or Navigator "Refresh" context menu item
to tell Eclipse that you've updated the files.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Building with other IDEs">
<p>
The same caveats apply as for Eclipse, above.
</p>

<p>
The same general idea should work in most IDEs; it has been reported
to work in Idea, for example.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
