<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="connectors.html">

    &project;

    <properties>
        <author email="remm@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
        <title>Connectors How To</title>
    </properties>

<body>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>Choosing a connector to use with Tomcat can be difficult. This page will
list the connectors which are supported with this Tomcat release, and will
hopefully help you make the right choice according to your needs.</p>

</section>

<section name="Standalone HTTP/1.1">

<p>The HTTP connector is setup by default with Tomcat, and is ready to use.</p>

</section>

<section name="Clustered HTTP/1.1">

<p>The HTTP connector is setup by default with Tomcat, and is ready to use. A HTTP 
load balancer <b>with support for web sessions stickiness</b> must be installed to
direct the traffic to the Tomcat servers.</p>

<p>
Tomcat supports mod_proxy (included by default in Apache httpd 2.2) as the load 
balancer. This version of mod_proxy can also be used with Apache httpd 2.0. It should
be noted that the performance of HTTP proxying is usually lower than the performance
of AJP, so AJP clustering is often preferable.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Standalone AJP">

<p>When using a single server, the performance when using a native webserver in 
front of the Tomcat instance is most of the time significantly worse than a
standalone Tomcat with its default HTTP connector, even if a large part of the web
application is made of static files. If integration with the native webserver is 
needed for any reason, an AJP connector will provide faster performance than 
proxied HTTP.</p>

<p>The native connectors supported with this Tomcat release are:
<ul>
<li>mod_jk 1.2.x</li>
<li>mod_proxy on Apache httpd 2.2, with AJP support</li>
</ul>
</p>

</section>

<section name="Clustered AJP">

<p>AJP clustering is the most efficient from the Tomcat perspective. It is otherwise
functionally equivalent to HTTP clustering.</p>

</section>

</body>

</document>
