<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="filter.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Container Provided Filters</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">

  <p>Tomcat provides a number of <strong>Filters</strong> which may be
  configured for use with all web applications using
  <code>$CATALINA_BASE/conf/web.xml</code> or may be configured for individual
  web applications by configuring them in the application's
  <code>WEB-INF/web.xml</code>. Each filter is described below.</p>

    <blockquote><em>
    <p>This description uses the variable name $CATALINA_BASE to refer the
    base directory against which most relative paths are resolved. If you have
    not configured Tomcat for multiple instances by setting a CATALINA_BASE
    directory, then $CATALINA_BASE will be set to the value of $CATALINA_HOME,
    the directory into which you have installed Tomcat.</p>
    </em></blockquote>

</section>


<section name="Set Character Encoding Filter">

  <subsection name="Introduction">

    <p>User agents don&apos;t always include character encoding information in
    requests. Depending on the how the request is processed, usually the
    default encoding of ISO-8859-1 is used. This is not always
    desirable. This filter provides options for setting that encoding or
    forcing it to a particular value. Essentially this filter calls
    <code>ServletRequest.setCharacterEncoding()</code> method.</p>

    <p>Effectively the value set by this filter is used when parsing parameters
    in a POST request, if parameter parsing occurs later than this filter. Thus
    the order of filter mappings is important. Note that the encoding for GET
    requests is not set here, but on a <strong>Connector</strong>. See
    CharacterEncoding page in the FAQ for details.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Filter Class Name">

    <p>The filter class name for the Set Character Encoding Filter is
    <strong><code>org.apache.catalina.filters.SetCharacterEncodingFilter</code></strong>.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Initialisation parameters">

    <p>The Set Character Encoding Filter supports the following initialization
    parameters:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="encoding" required="true">
        <p>Name of the character encoding which should be set.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="ignore" required="false">
        <p>Determines if any character encoding specified by the user agent is
        ignored. If this attribute is <code>true</code>, any value provided by
        the user agent is ignored. If <code>false</code>, the encoding is only
        set if the user agent did not specify an encoding. The default value
        is <code>false</code>.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Failed Request Filter">

  <subsection name="Introduction">

    <p>This filter triggers parameters parsing in a request and rejects the
    request if some parameters were skipped during parameter parsing because
    of parsing errors or request size limitations (such as
    <code>maxParameterCount</code> attribute in a
    <a href="http.html">Connector</a>).
    This filter can be used to ensure that none parameter values submitted by
    client are lost.</p>

    <p>Note that parameter parsing may consume the body of an HTTP request, so
    caution is needed if the servlet protected by this filter uses
    <code>request.getInputStream()</code> or <code>request.getReader()</code>
    calls. In general the risk of breaking a web application by adding this
    filter is not so high, because parameter parsing does check content type
    of the request before consuming the request body.</p>

    <p>Note, that for the POST requests to be parsed correctly, a
    <code>SetCharacterEncodingFilter</code> filter must be configured above
    this one. See CharacterEncoding page in the FAQ for details.</p>

    <p>The request is rejected with HTTP status code 400 (Bad Request).</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Filter Class Name">

    <p>The filter class name for the Failed Request Filter is
    <strong><code>org.apache.catalina.filters.FailedRequestFilter</code></strong>.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Initialisation parameters">

    <p>The Failed Request Filter does not support any initialization parameters.</p>

  </subsection>

</section>


</body>


</document>
